<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE refentry PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.1.2//EN" 
               "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.1.2/docbookx.dtd">
<refentry id="goocanvas-architecture">
  <refmeta>
    <refentrytitle>Underlying Architecture</refentrytitle>
    <manvolnum>3</manvolnum>
    <refmiscinfo>GOOCANVAS Library</refmiscinfo>
  </refmeta>

  <refnamediv>
    <refname>Underlying Architecture</refname>
    <refpurpose>how the canvas fits together.</refpurpose>
  </refnamediv>

  <refsect1 id="architecture">
    <title>Underlying Architecture</title>

    <refsect2 id="widget">
      <title>The GooCanvas Widget</title>
      <para>
	#GooCanvas is a #GtkWidget (it is actually a subclass of
	#GtkContainer), and so can be placed in an interface just like
	any normal widget. Usually a #GooCanvas widget would be placed inside
	a #GtkScrolledWindow in order to enable scrolling of the canvas.
      </para>
      <para>
	The size of the canvas can be set explicitly using
	goo_canvas_set_bounds(), or if the #GooCanvas:automatic-bounds
	property is set to %TRUE the bounds will be automatically calculated
	to include all of the canvas items. The units used in the canvas can
	be set with the #GooCanvas:units property. The canvas units can be
	pixels, points, inches or millimeters and apply to the canvas and
	all items.
      </para>
    </refsect2>

    <refsect2 id="simple-structure">
      <title>The Structure of the Simple Canvas</title>
      <para>
	The simple canvas consists of a hierarchy of canvas items.
	The root item is automatically created by the canvas and can be
	accessed using goo_canvas_get_root_item(). New items and groups can
	then be created and added to the root item.
      </para>
      <para>
	Each item in the canvas keeps a #GooCanvasBounds structure which
	stores the bounding rectangle of the item and all of its descendants.
	This makes it easy to find out which items in the canvas need repainting
	or which item the mouse is over. (The bounds are stored in the canvas
	coordinate space, which is the coordinate space of the entire canvas,
	after any item transformation matrices have been applied.)
      </para>
    </refsect2>

    <refsect2 id="model-view-structure">
      <title>The Structure of the Model/View Canvas</title>
      <para>
	The model/view canvas consists of a hierarchy of item models, and an
	identical hierarchy of canvas items, with each canvas item
	corresponding to one item model.
      </para>
      <para>
	The hierarchy of item models can be used in several #GooCanvas
	widgets, to allow multiple views of the same model.
	Though different canvas items will be used in each #GooCanvas.
      </para>
      <para>
	The root item model is set with goo_canvas_set_root_item_model().
	The canvas will automatically create canvas items to display
	the hierarchy of item models, and will automatically add and
	remove canvas items as the item model hierarchy is changed.
      </para>
    </refsect2>

    <refsect2 id="updates">
      <title>The Update Procedure</title>
      <para>
	When items are added to the canvas or their properties are changed
	they may need to recalculate their bounds. To do this they set an
	internal flag such as @need_update, and make a call to
	goo_canvas_item_request_update().
      </para>
      <para>
	#GooCanvas handles all the update requests at once, to avoids multiple
	redraws of the same parts of the canvas. To do this it installs
	an idle handler, goo_canvas_idle_handler(), which is called as soon
	as the application is idle (and before any part of the canvas is
	redrawn). 
      </para>
      <para>
	The idle handler calls goo_canvas_item_update() on the root item,
	which recursively calls goo_canvas_item_update() on any items as
	necessary, recalculating their bounds and requesting redraws as
	appropriate.
      </para>
      <para>
	If a container item (e.g. #GooCanvasGroup) is changed it needs to
	ensure that all descendants recalculate their bounds so it
	calls goo_canvas_item_update() for all of its children with the
	@entire_tree argument set to %TRUE.
      </para>
    </refsect2>

    <refsect2 id="simple-updates">
      <title>How Changes to Items are Handled</title>
      <para>
	When an item is changed (e.g. if the #GooCanvasRect:x property of
	a #GooCanvasRect is changed), the item calls
	goo_canvas_item_simple_changed() with a flag indicating if the
	bounds of the item need	to be recalculated.
      </para>
      <para>
	If the bounds don't need to be recalculated, then
	goo_canvas_request_redraw() is called to simply request that the
	item is redrawn. This results in a call to gdk_window_invalidate_rect()
	and the redraw proceeds just like a normal #GtkWidget.
      </para>
      <para>
	However, if the bounds do need to be recalculated then
	goo_canvas_item_request_update() is called to request that the item
	be updated the next time the canvas performs an update.
      </para>
    </refsect2>

    <refsect2 id="model-view-updates">
      <title>How Changes are Handled in the Model/View Canvas</title>
      <para>
	In the Model/View canvas it is the underlying item models which are
	initially changed. The item models emit "changed" signals which the
	items respond to. For the standard canvas items the
	goo_canvas_item_model_simple_changed() signal handler is called,
	which calls goo_canvas_item_simple_changed() and the
	procedure continues as in the simple canvas case above.
      </para>
    </refsect2>

  </refsect1>
</refentry>
